<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://haydarjawad.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://haydarjawad.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-24T23:22:49+00:00</updated><id>https://haydarjawad.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The P versus NP problem</title><link href="https://haydarjawad.github.io/blog/2024/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The P versus NP problem"/><published>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://haydarjawad.github.io/blog/2024/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://haydarjawad.github.io/blog/2024/distill/"><![CDATA[<h1 style="text-align: center; color:yellow !important;">P and NP problem: What is the Fuss All About?</h1> <h5 id="haydar-jawad-may-2024">Haydar jawad, May 2024</h5> <h4 id="what-is-an-algorithm">What is an Algorithm?</h4> <p>An algorithm is like a recipe or a set of instructions that tells a computer how to solve a problem. For example, if you want to bake a cake, the recipe gives you step-by-step directions. Similarly, an algorithm gives step-by-step directions to solve a problem or perform a task.</p> <h4 id="tiny-but-powerful">Tiny but Powerful:</h4> <p>Even small algorithms can solve very important and complicated problems. For example, the algorithm used for encrypting data (keeping information safe and private) is based on prime numbers and is very short but extremely powerful.</p> <h4 id="example-of-a-tiny-algorithm">Example of a Tiny Algorithm:</h4> <p>There’s a famous algorithm for testing whether a number is a prime (a number that has no divisors other than (1) and itself). This algorithm can be written in just a few lines but is very powerful because it helps secure online transactions.</p> <p>(P) vs (NP) Problem:</p> <p>On (P=NP) problem, one can asks whether every problem that can be checked quickly by a computer can also be solved quickly by a computer. This is one of the biggest unanswered questions in computer science.</p> <p>Imagine you have a really difficult puzzle. (P=NP) is like asking if there’s a super-fast way to solve the puzzle, not just check if a solution is correct.</p> <h4 id="challenge-in-proving-pnp">Challenge in Proving (P≠NP):</h4> <p>Proving that there is no quick solution for certain problems (like SAT, which involves solving logical puzzles) is very hard. Even proving that there isn’t a short algorithm for these problems is a big challenge.</p> <h3 id="why-it-matters">Why It Matters:</h3> <p>Understanding whether (P=NP) is important because if someone finds a fast algorithm to solve these hard problems, it could change the world. For example, it could break the encryption that keeps our online data safe, or it could help solve many other complex problems quickly.</p> <h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h4> <p>Algorithms may be small, but they are essential for solving big problems in our world. The quest to understand the (P=NP) problem is crucial for the future of computing and technology.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[P and NP problem: What is the Fuss All About?]]></summary></entry></feed>